[Music]
okay so what's the right pronunciation
how do I make sure I get this right
going forward you did it the third one
codo codo okay makes sense Cod s go got
it awesome well thanks so much for for
joining us to uh teach us about uh what
you've been working on here and I'm
going to give you the stage so you can
get right to uh teaching us about um
what this whole notion of flow
engineering is yeah my pleasure uh so by
the way yes it's also about quality code
that's one of the reasons for Cotto
actually Cotto mostly stands for quality
of development um I can share a bit
about my background and why how we came
to that uh name and by the way codium AI
uh now we call only our models like
basically how we see it like codium is
the base of code and for example the llm
that's what they understand they
understand line of code pretty pretty
well but not the entire software
development workflow and that's what we
are trying to do at Cotto enabling
developers to exploit ey also for code
review code testing and and generally
increasing the quality of development so
that's the a lot behind the the renaming
but I'm not here to talk about Cotto at
all I'm here to talk about the idea of
like you mentioned um moving from prompt
engineering to flow engineering and what
you can gain uh by by doing that by the
way I'm not going to talk about uh the
technicalities on what are the you know
for example framework that you can use
in order to do that um there there're
quite a few uh these days for example
Lang graph is one one of them rather
more about the philosophy and motivation
and and what you can benefit uh by
shifting from prompt engineering to flow
engineering I'm also going uh sec I'm
also going to to talk about the llms you
know just very basic although I think
everybody here know about them um just
in order to create some M Mutual context
and uh and then give a talk about a
framework of thinking uh and use that to
observe observe uh some of the latest uh
models
um like 01 and Sonet 3.5 and then
obviously like uh that's what we came to
talk about is Alpha codium is the
framework that released by Cotto almost
a year ago uh a bit less like early 2024
um it's open- sourced tool with which
you can win coding competition get a
Master Level 95% percentile of the
competitors uh with this Tool uh we just
released like a month ago an update uh
that works together with 01 um and then
I'm going to elaborate about about that
so first about llms um you know if we
take a a block uh of llm just just as a
blackbox like we mentioned you get an
input as a natural language description
or code and the output for example is
generated code as an example and this uh
block uh this uh um creature statistical
creature was uh trained with for example
a big uh BN bunch of of Open Source
repos hopefully in in many cases uh but
with permissive data Etc and inside it
uh it has a block in charge of to
tokenization like taking the natural
language description or the code and
tokenizing it into vectors because
that's how lmms know you know the best
how how they work with with vectors by
the way it's it's also in the in the
entrance and at the output taking the
vector back back to code and inside
we're learning patterns um so that's
important like all that it's in charge
is learning patterns so basically it's
so critical what's coming in what's
what's the pattern on which it was
trained that that's what's going to
influence what you're going to have in
that output so like that's so like basic
concept that we we must uh uh understand
that basically all it does is match
what's the right pattern uh for for the
input and and and the data data great
and that's bring us to to the limitation
of of llms like if you use them as is
like a black box it's hard for them to
handle uh complex challenges they
overfit to patterns that that's what
they do by by the way okay they're
supposed to fit to patterns but but
basically um in in many cases like
they're giving you the average uh and of
of a certain for a certain input and not
necessarily considering all edge cases
or everything that you would want to
consider if you did not provide it as
part of the context okay um so
overfitting for um uh one
second one
second sorry and so uh another thing is
like maintaining code consistency like
you you could you cannot expect the llm
uh for to do it for you just you know
having the same code cons consistency uh
if if you uh had a same piece piece of
code uh and some uh somewhere around
your code base and you're asking for for
the same thing um then it would not know
how to maintain a consistency unless you
had like a product around it like a
solution around it asking uh for it uh
um so so that's like a um so that's like
another a third limitation and the
fourth one is handling uh errors and and
debugging so again here is like think
about the patterns if you give it a
limited context and it doesn't get like
all it needs in order to understand how
to debug what to debug how to handle it
will not do it by itself okay so that's
uh that that's it now with like right
right now like a lot of the limitation
that I talked about is around like
missing context but what I didn't talk
about is also uh how hard it is to
actually do these like overcome these
four limitations without the capability
to to reason um so like like us people
we even if we collect a lot of uh
context the relevant context we still
need to to reason in order to overcome
these challenges and that was actually
another blocker that we had until
recently we might still have it uh but
uh uh but we actually got a couple of
new exciting models that are doing um
much better than than before I I know
that there is a lot of uh uh um amazing
new tools that were released recently um
for example I I'm I'm really excited to
be the one that talking after Eric the
CEO of ball. new I just recorded a
podcast with him it's coming out like in
in in 10 days at the Latin space um
podcast and and and like I think like
one of the main reason that these tools
are working now and they could not work
around like let's say 12 months ago is
because these models that we see we saw
recently are becoming extremely good um
for example in understanding like
snippet of code and also being able to
reason on it in a reasonable level now
um specifically open AI took it a one
step further and they said that 01 model
is actually unlocking system to
capability um like and and what do do
they mean by that is something that I
want to discuss next and I'm going to
claim that they kind of exaggerated okay
okay it's uh I I I think that by the end
of this uh talk and I'll leave a time
for Q&A obviously um we uh will believe
we will see that we have more to achieve
in order to unlock system system two
okay so that's what we're going to talk
about so what what is system one system
two and I'm adding system 1.5 first
let's talk about the origin of the this
ter terminology So Daniel kahanan um
like a Nobel Prize winner unfor un ly
like passed away last year uh he he
built a framework and you can read about
it and thinking fast to slow that's the
best place to to read about it in my
opinion um we like trying to split uh
how human think into two type of system
one is like very fast reactive to
outputs almost euristic like almost
using our our uh automatic response for
example how we behave after we starting
to to drive uh for for a while like
after you know the early days if you
remember when you're driving you really
really focused and maybe after 10 years
it's almost automatic and then system
two is more analytical methodical uh
slow uh decision-making um it's it's
more for complex problem it's it's kind
of a autonomous in a way autonomous is
in a way that uh it's it's like you
you're you are not you know right now
what I'm doing right now I'm doing for
example system one and kind of giving
the the next context next uh um you know
um sorry what I what I'm claiming that
what I'm doing now is doing system one
maybe 1.5 we're going to talk about it
and basically according to my previous
uh tokens I'm providing the next tokens
okay um and and that's like very
autonomic right but also system to
despite being a slow thinker Etc it's
still trying to navigate automatically
within the environment in order not to
just provide the next token but actually
complete uh complete a task or complete
a full uh decision making uh so that
that's a very a big a big difference uh
now um what we saw with a 01 model is
basically um kind of a Chain of Thought
um process it's like not only thinking
about the next few tokens but actually
thinking if if the model should further
think harder on the next few tokens
should it think on on a couple of tokens
uh that uh make sense to uh think about
and then if it didn't reach to the final
conclusion to keep thinking another
another iteration I don't think that
system to uh thinking at all and I'm
going to elaborate it um I I don't think
for example that this model is
environment aware uh if it it doesn't
get enough context it won't necessarily
understand that it's missing context Etc
while we human if you're thinking about
yourself when you're trying to solve a
code problem uh like not necessarily
writing more lines of code but solving
like a full feature one of the things
that you're doing is trying to realize
if you have enough information what
you're trying to collect the understand
the tools you're going to use Etc it
it's not being done on on the Fly for
example and with oan model okay so I I
want to like actually double down on
that because uh that's important I'm
going to show you like a re really high
level architecture uh of uh of a gen
system uh okay some of you might say
okay I'm now losing confidence in ITR
because he's showing the most trivial uh
solution out there it's like an input
and then like uh just Gathering context
and and prompting a model and and there
is an output but notice something like
extremely important uh that uh there is
like a field on the input and there is a
field on the output it's not like a very
specific uh like definition of what
we're trying to achieve and a very
specific uh output and that's what's
unique in many of the Gen system uh like
the prompt is not well defined the
context is not well defined and the
output could be very vague I think it's
very clear when you're talking about for
example image generation uh make me a
porcupine riding a llama with a moon uh
behind and you won't care too much right
on on the output uh like I mean like you
want it to be high quality but there's
not a one composition that that fits
fits them all okay and uh and well you
will still accept and that's why we're
so excited about this like models and
and system that are system one is good
enough um when you're trying to think
about system 1.5 for example what we're
seeing with 01 um or you can combine
your own by yourself we're going to see
that with alac codium you're you're
trying to chain uh a few inferences and
also use tools at this point you can try
to steer uh you can try to steer the
system to also try to clarify what is
the input and also uh by that trying to
be more specific on on the output if I
go back to the request of porcupine
writing a llama whatever a system 1.5
could say hey uh there's three different
composition there could be more but I'm
just giving an example would you like it
like this or or like that right and uh
it could be like a Chain of Thought to
to to try to to understand what's
appealing uh for example for for the
user so that's system 1.5 uh thinking
what when you're talking about system
two it's it's more than that it's it's
an agent um that that's you could
consider it like as a buzzword but but
what I'm trying to say that it's it's a
creature or a machine that is trying to
consider the environment that is around
him with additional information uh and
tools maybe uh considering other agents
and considering the overall um known and
unknown in the system it's aware that
it's part of of a bigger system and it's
try to apply Frameworks uh of thinking
like Daniel kahanan say like when you're
trying to deal with a with a quite a big
uh uh problem with important one you for
example try to understand what's the
environment what are what are your goals
what what what is available to you Etc
that will be like a system to Thinking
by the way I'm not saying that we can
get there I actually think we we could
and should but I don't think that's the
case with uh with all1 and let's try to
give some evidence so we're going to
look at code forces code contests uh
together with uh uh that's that's like
one of the most uh I don't know
prominent um uh like coding uh Pro
coding competition that you can find out
there you can go Google it code forces
and specifically a deep mind collected
uh like a few contest into a benchmark
called code code contest what we did at
Alpha codium is competed on this code
contest automatically together with a
great like competitors like uh deep mind
uh and uh uh open Ai and meta and
Salesforce and I think we're kind of the
fifth we saw sta Academy also competing
there and um I think like what I want to
tell you is that with 01 and I'm going
to show you results we're seeing like an
inching uh closer to system two than
what we have in in system one we do see
an 01 like kind of a guided thinking
like a Chain of Thought as I mentioned
we see like some kind of reasoning uh we
do see uh like that it's taking well
like a uh well structured problem and
and managing to reason uh on it I might
show you if we have time like an example
of of one of these uh there's still
obviously hallucinations that is going
on there and we see like people talking
about it I saw a very cool MIM uh where
um you see like uh someone writing a
skateboard and crashing that's
hallucination of uh gp4 o and then the
same skater managing to jump over a few
uh steps uh doing some Loops but then
crashing again and that's sometimes how
you feel when you use 01 it's like does
a few a few step uh it looks good it's
reasoning on on the problem but
eventually still hallucinating um so so
we are inching closer and we do see like
less hallucination but sometimes a
really magnificent ucation instead of
like a simple one okay so what do we do
with Alpha codium in Alpha codium we
said Hey in all these like cases where
other competitors are trying uh like
other companies are trying to compete on
a code contest what they're basically
doing is trying to force the model
itself to move from system one to system
1.5 thinking uh or or they Tred to
system to but we we're claiming that
they manag to system 1.5 and what we're
trying to do is say hey with all the
respect uh we humans are the system
twoth thinkers and the model are not
that good that yet so let's put a
framework of how a developer would solve
this we call it a flow and then with
each each node in the flow let's have an
llm like solve the problem so what you
can see here on the screen is our
attempt at Coto to develop a flow where
uh
uh that tries to actually mimic try to
uh do the same exact step that we as
developer would try to tackle problem in
the coding competition so it start from
un like taking the problem and there's a
few tests by the way the problem coming
with a couple sometimes zero sometimes
five tests and then it reflects on the
problem like you would do you're trying
to understand what did you actually read
and then you you take a look on on the
few tests that you're giv and and you're
trying to reason on them as well oh oh
that's what the problem actually meant
and then you're trying to think of
different solution you want to come up
with right uh let's write for example
four seoc code ideas on how I'm going to
solve the solution and then you're
ranking like what do I want to start
with which one is the best then you you
might if you're trying to do like kind
of tdd then you might want to try to
generate a few more tests like create
manually and that's what our system is
trying to do and then you're going to
finally write down the program you're
going to run the test on them and you're
going to see if the program actually
works uh if it does let's keep on
working on the tests that are round
truth that we're giving as part of the
problem and then iterate over the test
that were actually generated by AI by
Alpha codium until finally you reach the
solution um I don't see the chat right
now but you can write there uh and and
tell me I I'll soon stop sharing if this
is how you would tackle the problem but
that's how we thought to tackle it and
interestingly um that that by building
this flow we got we gained a lot of uh
other uh things other good properties
that we didn't think about
for example the fact that each prompt in
each node in each one of those steps is
actually smaller it it's like or maybe
say like it's it's less um the the
variant for the variance of changing a
word or adding a line or removing a line
from a prompt actually is is small the
the models are are less sens sens
sensible to sensitive sorry uh to to a
certain word that was selected that
actually when you trying to do direct
prompting like just prompt engineering
it could be very very sensitive but when
you broke the problem into many blocks
in this case supposedly 10 actually
there is 12 we're trying to simplify
here that actually The Prompt Care is
matters less and that was important we
spent 25% of our time on engineering
this flow and only 5% on the prompt
engineering itself because it matter
less and interestingly also it was less
important what exact model we we were
trying we tried with uh deep seek
actually the the old model not maybe the
newest 3.5 uh Sonet 3.5 I think this is
not the latest latest son 3.5 but the
one before uh turbo GPD or and we we
noticed that we didn't need to change
the prompt so much uh so that's like one
of the takeaway I want to tell you from
from today that if you are leaving uh
the 01 model um to do all the Thinking
by itself first you're going to be very
dependent on the model and very
dependent on the on the prompt and if
you um design your workflow yourself you
can be less prompt uh um uh let's say
sensitive and and and then like the
prompt is also being simplified what you
see here on the x-axis are different
models and on the Y AIS is the accuracy
on the coding contest just to let you
know reaching around 78% uh like
accuracy solving 78% of the problem is
95 percentile among professional
developers or sorry among developers
that are competing on the coding contest
um what you see here um that the purple
is using a certain model with Alpac
codium and competing with roughly the
same amount of inference calls like
computation efforts when doing direct
prompting by the way the right prompting
is usually when we really worked hard to
to to bring a good a good prompt what's
interesting uh here is that we do see
for example 01 Excel over GPD 40 um by
the way like being double in accuracy is
much more than double of of of problem
solving in in the real world because
actually the problems obviously if gp4 o
solved 23 23% of the problem it solved
the easier Parts okay and then uh if it
like uh the the higher you go like the
78 perti for example you're seeing on
the right sorry 78% accuracy versus 55
it's more than 50% better it's like much
better uh because the it's dealing with
like another 23% of problem that are
really really hard um just to let you
know we didn't get access or we didn't
ask for it to be frank but uh for 01 the
regular one or 01 II it's it's 01 II is
actually a model trained by open ey to
specifically fit for this coding contest
an Olympic uh like uh math uh olymp
sorry and uh uh competition and and
actually what's interesting if if you
use 01 preview with Alpha codium it
reaches higher results than than the
best model that was actually fine-tuned
you know for for this problem this shows
like like it makes it for me like a
strong evidence that these models are
not system to because what do we have
here in Alpha codium not much right like
uh they could supposedly come up with
with this uh framework themselves so if
they're not able to think through to
build these kind of processes uh then
then obviously they're not system uh uh
to that's that's what one of the
evidence that I'm bringing here um I
didn't dive into each one of those
modules is part I'm going like to to
show like only only one which is the
testing which is the hardest part and
maybe the most critical one so I'm going
to do that via visualization let's say
that we're taking one problem in the
competition that's the the purple uh
sorry let's say we're taking one problem
in the competition and we in an Oracle
an oracle give us the correct solution
and let's say like we visualize it as
this like purple um Cloud on on the left
now what happens if when you give like
the problem even including like uh
everything you can the best context and
and provide it to a direct prompt even
01 it will try to you know bring the
best solution it can it might be very
appealing uh and looks like like it
works but maybe there's some some skew
like just visually like trying to
explain this um and and there's a good
reason because there's like not enough
uh you know understanding and and and
and slow thinking and and using usage of
tools Etc um that we're going to talk
about that that is done with with direct
prompting prompting and models that are
only using AI uh analysis okay and now
in the middle what we're seeing here is
what if if we like provide a few tests
for example maybe they were given a part
of the coding coding contest and we
prompt the model uh to um you know make
sure that it answer that the the test
would pass that it works well for for
the test um by the way in this case you
can either for example do direct
prompting or half of alpha codium let's
say all the the green part on the left
that is without running the the code and
testing the code what we usually get is
overfitting to to to to fit for the
public test that the the few tests that
were given that's in the middle on the
right what you see here is the um
attempt to generate additional tests not
only generate like like obvious tests
but actually even trying to generate
edge cases specifically this is a hard
task now by the way you can say like oh
if the model is able to generate test
why couldn't it uh generate the right
solution to start with hey the model is
not that far from how we we developers
behave can you write your code even if
you're writing it like perfectly uh
sorry even if you're thinking about it
thoroughly um can you write perfect code
without tests in many cases you would
need even sanity test or whatever let
alone like edge cases to find those
cases but hey it's the same you that
might be writing those edge cases is
because you apply different processes
and maybe even you you use different
tools to to make these and that's
exactly the idea in in Alpha code use
spe specific like maybe different
prompting and different tools to to
generate those test specifically and now
a Shameless plug that's one of the
reason at Cotto we focus so much on test
generation uh you can see like for
example our ID extension called koden
has like three and more more is coming
very soon uh stay tuned more test
generation option that we have that they
have the specific flows um to help you
generate those tests that's and when we
have other tools uh we have like a
multi-agent platform and koden and ID is
is one of them and and that's what we
specialize and and we have a lot more by
way to develop it's not perfect but
actually you could claim that if you
solve testing you solved software
development right and that's what you
can see here if we are able to properly
generate uh test uh and then uh uh you
can actually also uh generate better
Solutions okay and uh I'm not going to
dive deep in how to choose tests and how
to to check if they're wrong because if
they're wrong they could steer the the
you know the alpha codium for example to
get bad bad results um that you by the
way the tool is fully open source you
can read there I want to tell you one
last slide before we go to question that
Meta Meta also did an attempt their
research to to take a model and actually
they did something really awesome that
they they trained the model on data that
that is coming from execution of code so
like they did it with reinforcement
learning they kind of trying to teach
the model to to like to consider data
that is happening here in Alpha codium
like if the the DAT the the model
outputed a solution with with a with a
certain code and there was an attempt to
run a test and a test was failing then
that's a negative uh reinforcement for
the model and if it the test passed then
it's a positive reinforcement and also
they can use the the errors or the logs
so that's really really cool idea and it
actually does help like for example if
if you check like their their solution
it actually does better uh for example
with Alpha code with not the best model
out there but the thing is that I am
willing to bet on uh really high uh
amount of Teslas that if you take their
models and put it in Alpha codium
and run them both one against each other
uh uh even considering the same amount
of comput computation Alpha codium would
do better because still uh these system
this model are not yet really system to
thinkers and not that good and even I I
don't believe like they we nail it with
system 1.5 so Alpha codium 01 for
example is so high above this um you
know this figure by the way they use
their they use their Alpha codium from
from the first release now the latest
one so that's why they got the these
results uh great so that that's it my
takeaway um for for for you guys um is
for everyone everyone at home uh is hey
prompt engineering is cool but also uh
quite challenging every word matters try
to use these models like 01 Etc they
reason much better but at the same time
if you know how you would solve that
problem see if you can generate a graph
of flow
okay and for example using lra as an
example and then you would notice that
your accuracy is better you can put
guard rails along the way you can use
you can help the models use tools and
then the reasoning capabilities that we
see they're actually going to help you
uh uh get better results because even
with one node within the flow probably
reasoning capabilities is important but
don't trust the reasoning capabilities
of the models these days to do for you
the entire system to sying or or so
awesome thank you so much it's been F
fascinating to see kind of you share a
bunch of the the data here it's actually
great timing on the sessions by the way
because Demetri is coming up next has
will be showing a project that lets you
actually set up and wire up all of these
flows so you can quickly kind of
experiment with awesome this in
different ways and uh it was interesting
to see that you know 01 and the like of
like I hadn't thought about baking some
of these pieces you of reasoning into
the model itself and have been more
involved in doing the metacognition on
the outside and the uh the intuition on
the inside and so it's kind of fun to
see now both evolving at the uh at the
same time so thanks so much for uh
showing that so we have some uh
questions that we'd love to to get to
here let's get to this first one because
it it's uh just asking Bas on something
you were kind of just talking about near
the end there okay Mike yeah
yeah okay yes it's it's uh I would I
would say that it's either doing tdd or
doing bdd to some extent um like
basically there are three components
that I think we have um three type of
files meta file that we're using when
you're doing doing software development
we have the specifications right uh like
for example they can appear at figma I
would call that specification we have
the code and we have the the test these
are the three types like like we some
people like would consider TD to be uh
start with the tests right and then
maybe uh you know do the specification
in code or only the code Etc so I think
like what's happening right here in um
in Alpha codium is actually we start
with the spec for example there is an
iteration that try to understand the
problem and then from the spec we're
moving to the tests and then from the
tests we're moving to the code and
actually I think uh um this is a very
plausible way uh to think of how the
future of software Dev look like
although I think that life is hard and
uh in many cases and basically we
developers would love to have all
options open to us sometimes I want to
start with the test because I want to
make sure that these this is what I want
to make sure that it's working and then
I want the AI to help me to do spec and
then code sometime I want to start with
a test to do code and then spec sometime
I want to spec to code so I believe that
you will see different solution coming
with with different like uh Direction
and some solution will enable you all
the directions specifically at Cotto we
believe that fortunately and
unfortunately different type of software
development would benefit from different
directions specifically for coding
contest you want to solve the problem so
you're starting with analyzing the the
the problem that you're trying to solve
you got that and anyway the spec then
yeah let's move that to testing and then
moving to to code so t D like if I have
to choose yes or no the answer is yes
but actually I think it's more like a
spec DD uh or or bdd or a business
D got it Y is asking how do you evaluate
your flows what made you decide that
particular uh setup was the right flow
that's a great question and as I
mentioned we worked like 95% of our time
on um on designing the flow rather on
the prompt because we saw that a good
flow requires less time on on prompting
um so um first of all like there is the
the beginning and the end like you have
that the the test that you need to pass
uh right um by the way the really
interesting in my opinion cool thing
about the coding contest competition is
that some of the tests that you're
measured on are private we do not see it
you need to submit so it's harder to to
to uh it's harder for like PE for like
really good organizations to try to
overfit or to train on that uh uh and
what we see with some of the Benchmark
being like like overfitted because the
data is out there and in code contest
the testing data like there there is a
test data set that is not given given to
you uh so you you use your like for
example your validation test that are
given by the competition in order to try
to to generate a flow so that's the
beginning and the end but I think you
ask a m really awesome question that can
be applied to other how do we know the
middle like we can remove move one or
another and and and then like uh it
could help at the end or not but maybe
actually the problem is that we change
something in the middle it actually does
create a better result but the next node
just is not the appropriate one to to
change it so what I suggest is to
putting some kind of your own criteria
on on on nodes in the middle for example
um when you when you're thinking about
uh for for example there was one step
that is trying to to to change the
problem description into technical
problem description so you can say hey I
have a few measures on how I want the
structure to be like on or what do I
appreciate some of them can be measured
like non-statistically but some of them
you can use judges llm as judges so you
can take like gimin Gemini uh and GPT
and Sonet or whatever and like check
tell them okay according to this
criteria how good uh was the output of
this node Accord like uh and and and
then like iterate on that no node alone
some criteria are could you could put
that are not statistically based I mean
like you don't have to use a model to do
that but for some of them fortunately
unfortunately you need like a technique
like using llm as judges and it's
actually not aad bad technique you need
to think about your criteria well and
then it might work quite well got it
awesome thank you so much we've got a
few more questions that we won't be able
to get to on the stream but we'll be
able to jump into the Discord I'm also
here thinking about just wanting to chat
to you about generating high quality
tests and finding edge cases because so
many of the tools just kind of generate
somewhat route boring simple tests it's
that's the CH doing things so I think
there's I'm so excited that you're
focused on the testing space and uh
looking forward to talking about that
but idmr thank you so much for your time
really appreciate it and look forward to
talking to testing and code review
review is like also like a very
important part of thank you thank you
everyone really awesome to be here and
listen to all others